<?xml version="1.0"?>
<page subtopic="Software projects" topic="Pairs" layout="../../menu.xml">
  <title>Pairs</title>

  <text>
    <h3>Pairs</h3>
    
    <p>
      The <class>Pair</class> class represents a scheme pair. It consists of a
      <variable>Car</variable> and a <variable>Cdr</variable> field, which can
      both be any type of object. As far as Scheme itself is concerned, this is
      all there is to a pair.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      However, a scheme pair has a few properties that can be better exposed via
      .NET interfaces. Consequently, the <class>Pair</class> implements the
      <interface>IList</interface>, allowing it to be used in many circumstances
      where a .NET list class can be. There are some 'oddities' related to the
      slightly differing nature of a Pair to a 'standard' .NET list which may
      limit the usefulness of these functions.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Improper lists are not .NET lists. For convienience, no error is generated
      unless the 'improper' element is accessed, however, so improper lists may
      be useful in some circumstances. Neither are self-referential lists: these
      do not produce errors but may result in infinite loops in some cases.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The .NET list interface is designed on the assumption that the 'list' is
      contained by the class and is not (as in the case of Pairs) the class
      itself. This means that it is not sensible to remove the only element
      in a scheme list containing a single value. The .NET 'null' value
      represents an empty list, and the scheme specification states that
      an empty list is not a Pair. Use <code>myPair = myPair.Cdr</code> as code
      to remove the first element in a list wherever you possibly can.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Normally removing (or inserting) an element will just result in an elements
      Cdr being changed, but this is not always possible, so some operations will
      result in an element being overwritten. In particular, inserting or
      removing at the beginning of a Pair list will result in the first element
      being overwritten with the new value. The consequences are subtle, but
      may be significant in some circumstances.
    </p>
    
    <p align="center">
      <img src="removing-cdrs.png" /><br />
      <b>Consequences of removing parts of a Pair</b>
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Given the pair <scheme>(1 2 3)</scheme>, stored in the object <variable>somePair</variable>, 
      the result of <code>somePair.Remove(1)</code> is that somePair.Cdr is changed
      to point to <scheme>(3)</scheme> (the tail of the pair). <code>somePair.Cdr.Remove(0)</code>
      however, has a new effect. It changes the pair representing <scheme>(2 3)</scheme>
      (the Cdr of pair) with the pair <scheme>(3)</scheme>. <code>somePair.Cdr</code>
      is NOT changed, but instead its value is modified.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Pairs can be constructed from any object implementing the ICollection
      interface. This produces a well-formed scheme list from the contents
      of the collection.
    </p>
  </text>

  <footer>
    <p>
      Email: <a href="mailto:andrew@logicalshift.demon.co.uk">andrew@logicalshift.demon.co.uk</a>
    </p>
  </footer>
 </page>
 
